Finding Aid for Subcommittee on Human Use of Radioisotopes (University of Michigan) records, 1951-1985
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Subcommittee on Human Use of Radioisotopes (University of Michigan) records 1951-1985
University of Michigan. Subcommittee on Human Use of Radioisotopes.
3 linear feet
87364 Bimu B31 2
Subcommittee of the Radiation Policy Committee of the University of Michigan concerned with applications for the use of radioisotopes in humans. Chronological and topical files, applications, and files of subcommittee officers, Isadore Lampe, Charles S. Simons, and Ronald Bishop.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The material was received through Dr. Ronald Bishop (Donor No. 7217 ) in June of 1985
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Prior to I948. the use of radiation at the University of Michigan was focused an the diagnostic and therapeutic applications of X-ray machines and radium sources, with limited research being done in physics and chemistry using radioisotopes of relatively short lifetimes. A wider variety of radioisotopes became available from the Oak Ridge reactor after 1947; that same year, the Atomic Energy Commission of the United States released certain radioisotopes for institutional use in humans. In the Years following the A.E.C.'s decision, work involving the use of iodine isotopes on thyroid patients began at the University of Michigan. A new era of radiation research had begun.
On October 13, 1950, President Alexander Ruthven established the Radiation Policy Committee (R.P.C.) to discuss and make recommendations concerning all work with radiation and radioactive materials on the University of Michigan campus. At the same time, a Radiation Safety officer was appointed and the Radiation Control Service established to oversee such wo0: and to report to the Radiation Policy Committee. On June 4, 1952, the chairman of the R.P.C. appointed a Subcommittee on HL(man Use D~ Radioisotopes, to be responsible for approving or rejecting all applications for the use of radioisotopes in humans.
The Subcommittee initially met formally once a year. In between these annual meetings, applications were circulated among the members. Approval or rejection was indicated by telephone or memoranda. The Subcommittee began to meet much more frequently as the issues involved in research with radioactive materials became more complex, and as the bulk and number of applications increased. The Subcommittee chairmen were Isadore Lampe (1952-1962), Edward Carr (1962-1972), Ronald Bishop (1972-1985), and the Present chair, Brahm Shapiro (1995-). Since its inception in 1952, the Subcommittee has operated under guidelines established by the A.E.C. (now the Nuclear Regulatory Commission) and, since 1980-1981, by the Federal Drug Administration. In 1976, a Radioactive Drug Research Committee was established at the University of Michigan, to satisfy federal guidelines. To this point in time, its membership has coincided with the membership of the Subcommittee, and so distinctions between the two committees' activities are often hard to make. In addition, members of the Subcommittee are often also members of the parent Radiation Policy Commission.
The records of the Subcommittee on Human Use of Radioisotopes document the university's policies and procedures governing use of radioisotopes in treatment and research. The files include correspondence, memos, reports, application forms and meeting minutes. The records are divided into six series: Chronological Files, Topical Files, Applications (by Researcher), Applications (by Radioisotope), Applications (Chronological) and Officers' Files.
Subjects:
Radiation.; Radioisotopes.; University of Michigan. Radiation Policy Committee.; University of Michigan--Research.; University of Michigan. Subcommittee on Human Use of Radioisotopes.
Contributors:
Bishop, Ronald.; Lampe, Isadore, 1906-; Simons, Charles S.
- Chronological Files
  The Chronological Files cover the years 1968-1985 and contain such materials as correspondence, memos, reports, application forms and meeting minutes. The files do include some materials from the parent committee, the R.P.C., as well as from related committees such as the Radioactive Drug Research Committee. These files then serve as reference files for the Subcommittee as well as the official record of internal activity. The researcher should note that the Chronological files contain kinds of materials, like application forms and minutes, which are also found in other series.
  - 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - 1973-1979 (Box 1)
  - 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - 1982, 1983
    - General (Box 1)
    - Supporting Documents (Box 1)
  - 1984
    - General (Box 1)
    - Supporting Documents (Box 1)
  - 1985 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series is small and consists of one folder of material concerning proposed research at Dow Chemical and two folders relating to F.D.A. reviews of the Radiation Policy Committee and its related committees in 1981 and 1983.
  - Dow Chemical Study 1983 (Box 1)
  - F.D.A. Review
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - 1983 (Box 1)
- Applications 1952-1960
  The division of application forms into three series reflects the various filing arrangements practiced by the Subcommittee over time. There is very little actual overlap between the second and third series of applications, although the dates of coverage do overlap. The Applications (by Researcher) series is the earliest filing arrangement used by the Subcommittee and contains applications dating from 1952-1960. The second arrangement of Applications (by Radioisotope) covers the period 1961-1973 and contains files arranged alphabetically by abbreviations for the chemical element used in the research'. The researcher unfamiliar with these abbreviations should consult the table of elements included in this finding aid. This series includes an index file on 3 x 5 cards. Each card contains the researcher's name, project title, and chemical information for the isotope used. The third arrangement is found in the Applications (Chronological) series. This series covers the period 1954-1985, although the bulk of the files dates from 1970-1985. The application form required by the Subcommittee changed somewhat over the years covered by the three series, but taken together these three runs of applications provide a fairly comprehensive picture of radiation research involving human subjects from 1952 to the present. Each form provides basic information concerning the researcher, the research problem and strategy and the human Subjects.
  - By Researcher
    - Beierwaltes, William H. (Box 1)
    - Bennett, James E. (Box 1)
    - Bishop, Ronald C * (Box 1)
    - Christian, Halvor N. (Box 1)
    - Conn, Jerome W. (Box 1)
    - Dingledine, William S. (Box 1)
    - Dingman, Reed 0. (Box 1)
    - Dodson, Vernon N. (Box 1)
    - Dontas, A.S. (Box 1)
    - French, Arthur B. (Box 1)
    - Grabb, W. C. (Box 1)
    - Gurney, Clifford W. (Box 1)
    - Hartsook, J.T. (Box 1)
    - Henley, Keith S. (Box 1)
    - Kahn, Edgar (Box 1)
    - Kretzschmar, R.M. (Box 1)
    - Lewis, Louis W. (Box 1)
    - Liechty, Richard D. (Box 1)
    - Meyers, Muriel C. (Box 1)
    - Miller, R.F. (Box 1)
    - Nickerson, Mark (Box 1)
    - Oliver, William J. (Box 1)
    - Raccuglia, Giovanni (Box 1)
    - Reynolds, Robert M. (Box 1)
    - Roseman, Saul (Box 1)
    - Rovner, David R. (Box 1)
    - Schneider, Richard C. (Box 1)
    - Schteingart, David E. (Box 1)
    - Shapiro, Irving (Box 1)
    - Simons, Charles S. (Box 1)
    - Steude, Georgine M. (Box 1)
    - Streeten, David H.P. (Box 1)
    - Towsley, Harry (Box 1)
    - Verity, Gordon L. (Box 1)
    - Vial, A. Burgess (Box 1)
    - Wilson, William S. (Box 1)
  - By Radioisotopes
    (with index on 3x5 cards)
    - Ag (Silver)-I (Iodine), 13 folders (Box 2)
    - I (Iodine)-Yb (Ytterbium), 13 folders (Box 2)
- Applications. 1954-1985
  - Chronological 1954-1956
    - 1959 (Approvals) (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Approvals) (Box 2)
    - 1963 (Box 2)
    - 1964 (Box 2)
    - 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971 (Box 2)
    - 1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973 (Box 2)
    - 1974 (Box 2)
    - 1975 (Box 2)
    - 1976 (Box 2)
    - 1977 (Box 2)
    - 1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (folder no. 1) (Box 2)
    - 1982 (folder no. 2) (Box 3)
    - 1983 (Box 3)
    - 1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985 (Box 3)
- Officers' Files
  The Officers' Files series is comprised of the files kept by Dr. Isadore Lampe, chairman of the Subcommittee from 1952-1962; by Dr. Charles S. Simons, a Subcommittee member from 1953. until circa 19701, and secretary from 1957 until his retirement; and by Dr. Ronald Bishop, a member from 1959-1985 and chairman from 1972-1935. Simons' files in particular include minutes of Subcommittee meetings, sometimes in draft form, although each of the other subseries does as well. Lampe's and Bishop's files contain materials from Radiation Control Service and the Radiation Policy Committee. Bishop was a member of the R.P.C. as well as of the Subcommittee, and the researcher will find in the Bishop subseries chronological files documenting R.P.C. activities from 1977-1985. The Officers' Files in general thus provide a broader Picture of radiation research and concerns at the University of Michigan, since they are less limited to activities involving human use. For example, it is here that 'the researcher will find the most information on growing concern with radio-active waste disposal and employee safety issues. However, the researcher should be prepared to use this series in conjunction with the first series, Chronological Files. Each contains similar materials, such as minutes, correspondence and reports.
  - Lampe, Isadore (Chairman, 1952-1962)
    - A.E.C. Policy Notices, 1951-1960 (Box 3)
    - Radiation Control Service Annual Report 1953, 1955 (Box 3)
    - Subcommittee on Human Use of Radioisotopes
      - General 1952-1962 (Box 3)
      - Minutes 1952-1957 (Box 3)
  - Simons, Charles S.
    (Secretary, 1957-1970 ?; member, 1953-1970 ?)
    - Subcommittee on Human Use of' Radioisotopes 1952-1970 (Box 3)
  - Bishop, Ronald
    (Chairman, 1972-1985 member, 1959-1985)
    - Miscellaneous 1977-1985 (Box 3)
    - Radiation Control Service
      - Annual Report 1960-1961 (Box 3)
      - General 1957-1983 (Box 3)
      - Review Committee Report 1979, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Radiation Disaster Drill 1981 (Box 3)
  - Radiation Policy Committee
    - 1977 (Box 3)
    - 1978 (Box 3)
    - 1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
    - 1981 (Box 3)
    - 1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983 (Box 3)
    - 1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985 (Box 3)
    - License Renewal 1977 (Box 3)
  - Radioactive Drug Research Committee 1976-1982 (Box 3)
  - Subcommittee on Human Use of Radioisotopes
    - Europium Incident 1977 (Box 3)
    - General 1959-1978 (Box 3)
    - Membership 1973-1977 Minutes, 1964-1972 (Box 3)
  - Subcommittee to Review Applications and Amendments for Radioisotope Procurement 1983-1985 (Box 3)